[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is Samyutta Nikaya 7.2.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on one occasion, a Brahmin heard that another Brahmin had gone forth from the home life into homelessness in the presence of the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he sort of changed his religion there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this Brahmin, angered and displeased, went to the Blessed One and on arrival, insulted him with rude and harsh words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he was telling the Buddha off.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha says, What do you think, Brahman?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do friends or relatives come to you as guests?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, yes, they occasionally do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And do you serve them with food and drinks?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they don't accept those offerings, to whom do those offerings belong?
[SPEAKER_01]: If they don't accept them, the offerings still belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says, likewise, Brahman, we, who do not abuse anyone, who do not scold anyone, who do not quarrel against anyone, refuse to accept from you the abuse, the scolding and the quarrel that you let loose at us.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brahman, one who abuses his abuser, who scolds the one who scolds him, who fights against the one who fights with him, he is said to partake of the meal,
[SPEAKER_01]: to enter upon an exchange.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we not, we do not partake of your meal.
[SPEAKER_01]: We do not enter upon an exchange.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Brahman says, says, well, like, ooh, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: The king, together with his consort, know this of the master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gautama is the contemplative... Gautama is an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, master Gautama gets angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: So he's like,
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha replies, how can anger arise in one who's angerless?
[SPEAKER_01]: In the tamed one of righteous living?
[SPEAKER_01]: In one liberated by perfect knowledge?
[SPEAKER_01]: In the stable one who abides in peace?
[SPEAKER_01]: One who repays an angry man with anger, thereby makes things worse for himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not repaying an angry man with anger, one wins a battle hard to win.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a question, a few questions that I gathered from this, that others seem to be interested in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whenever I meet a certain rude person, I wish they're metta.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as much as I have done this, that person still remains rude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is the power of metta not working?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the first question.
[SPEAKER_05]: How would you answer that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not metta, what that means.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's correct.
[SPEAKER_05]: And any other way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if metta is supposed to make the other person not be rude anymore, then... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, metta is not working, because that's not where metta is supposed to work.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Friendliness is your framework of your mind, it's your attitude, it's your cultivation in face of rudeness and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the whole point of practicing metta is so that you don't give rise to anger or ill-will.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter how long the external abuse, rudeness and so on lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... that's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... and it sounds to me like this person is using metta as a retaliation, you know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, no, it's you using metta as a way out of the unpleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll do metta, so they'll stop being angry, so we're all friends again.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, because I dislike the discomfort of experiencing rudeness, which means I'm moved by it, I'm pressured by it, I'm not at peace internally when I experience those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, matter should shelter me from those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Matter should make you immovable in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, what I meant is, like, someone is having thoughts of kindness or trying to spread metta energy to the person, but that that whole attitude is one of trying to, like, attack or retaliate against that rudeness, rather than... Yeah, it's acting out, sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's acting out, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's partaking in that meal, just in a different way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is not metta.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you're still doing it because you're experiencing the unpleasantness of rudeness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, another kind of question that somebody might ask is like, if I'm doing Metta properly, I shouldn't be... it shouldn't even be uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It shouldn't be unpleasant for somebody to insult me or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I should just not care at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or can it still be, like, because you said, you don't want the discomfort of the anger, that's why you act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somebody might say, oh, but if I was doing it right, it shouldn't be uncomfortable at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not because I don't want...
[SPEAKER_05]: Right, right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_05]: The abusive words will remain abusive words.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it will be like heat, cold,
[SPEAKER_05]: Rain, wind, abusive words.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's going to be uncomfortable, but none of that discomfort can move the mind, or can make the mind re-engage willingly with ill-will.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it will remain imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just because the Buddha doesn't get angry in this case, doesn't mean it was like...
[SPEAKER_05]: He's unaware of the actions of that Brahmin, that he was rude and offensive.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, of course.
[SPEAKER_05]: If somebody comes in this room and I'm showering them with attitude of friendliness, is that spreading of metta?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is that then?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the showering then?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, like I'm sort of welcoming, doing all these things just to make them feel my friendship.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it's acting out of craving for...
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_05]: So then, when the Buddha says he
[SPEAKER_05]: Spreads matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pervades.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pervades the entire world with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pervades all the quarters with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that not the same?
[SPEAKER_05]: Pervading the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pervading individuals.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Pervading the groups.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like a negative.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's pervading and spreading, what I refer to.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is that the same or different?
[SPEAKER_04]: Different.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is pervading, then?
[SPEAKER_05]: How is pervading different from spreading?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, um, colloquially and, um... No, practically.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, say, we describe spreading of metta, showing your friendliness, engaging with it, thinking positive thoughts, all that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is pervading, then, if it's different than that?
[SPEAKER_05]: How would you do pervading?
[SPEAKER_05]: How would you pervade the world with your attitude of friendliness?
[SPEAKER_04]: Where is that done?
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Finished.
[SPEAKER_02]: Internally.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not done in the world that you assume of others, pervading the quarters.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's all done internally and it requires no acting out.
[SPEAKER_05]: It requires no overly showing these attitudes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Which are all rooted exactly in craving and wanting other person to be affected by your friendliness.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's not matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Matter is on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the up, down, east, west, in every direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do you have to travel physically to... No.
[SPEAKER_05]: You already are doing it internally.
[SPEAKER_05]: It just gets conflated.
[SPEAKER_05]: That type of pervading gets conflated with all these external acts.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, see, this is what is meant by that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like I'm pervading, I'm visualizing,
[SPEAKER_05]: And then I'm expressing it to everyone, everything, all the time.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's completely not what the matter is, because the same attitude of pervading, you know, you cultivate for all four brahma-vihāras.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how are you going to express your indifference?
[SPEAKER_05]: Equanimity.
[SPEAKER_05]: How are you going to pervade that onto the others?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or spread that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Spread them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Spread equanimity.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, well, that's not gonna be...
[SPEAKER_05]: Spread immovability.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's not spreadable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it is... you can pervade it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can pervade all quarters in your mind, in all directions, as far as your thought goes, with that attitude.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's a completely an internal practice, which is why exactly it will establish you in the dwelling of Brahmas.
[SPEAKER_05]: No matter what anyone does.
[SPEAKER_05]: No matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if you don't do anything externally, you just sit silently.
[SPEAKER_05]: Of course, if you spread such attitude internally, not externally, if you pervade all the quarters with that attitude, then, doesn't matter what comes through your senses, or who comes through your senses, that attitude will not be able to be perturbed.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's how you've successfully cultivated metta.
[SPEAKER_05]: When you're not perturbed by things, they would want to perturb you with ill-will and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it has absolutely nothing to do with other person, persons, at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: Otherwise, it's conditional on their actions, so... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: We said that before in those other talks, like, you know, so...
[SPEAKER_05]: When that, eh... when the Buddha says, and then you protect that state of mind, as a mother would protect a child.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, not protect random people.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mind of ill-will is your problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Being perturbed away from the wholesome state of mind of friendliness is your problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's where you stay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Guarding that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, another question is that I hear many people voicing their wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you partake in other people's actions?
[SPEAKER_05]: In other people's internal choices, are beings owners of their own actions, or they own a bit of their own actions, a bit of someone else's actions?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: None of that can be a problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: You are making it a problem by not being able to tolerate it, by not being able to not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you act out of your own craving, because other people hold all these wrong views rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you got your answer there.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, you could nearly just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you happen to hear other people or see other people doing some things that you find misguided or that you disagree with.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_05]: Assuming your duty to be... To be to correct those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if you kind of can take that to its conclusion, well, you're just going to have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Endless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's endless.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like you spend your entire life circling... Because vast majority will always remain in darkness, will always remain...
[SPEAKER_05]: With wrong views, we'll always remain misrepresenting the things, so... Enlightenment is not about correcting everybody else, just about fixing your own issue.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's how you practice for both.
[SPEAKER_05]: But that's a hard thing to accept, for somebody who still doesn't want to relinquish their own righteous craving.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, you say, Arahant practices for both, by becoming enlightened himself.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, no, but no, you must be more engaged with the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: You must bring social change, you must affect, you must correct them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Actually, no, you don't.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can, if you want to, but you better be aware of the reasons why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because they might well be the same reasons that these people have, because of which they're in such darkness.
[SPEAKER_05]: Craving and desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: Righteousness and blindness.
[SPEAKER_05]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that sutta, I think it's in the Majjhima Nikaya, where the Buddha is talking to two householders, lay people, and one of them, after a certain amount of time, says, okay, I have to go now, and he leaves, and then the Buddha says, you know, if he had stayed a bit longer, he would have seen the Dhamma and attained the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he didn't say anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it wasn't his.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't even say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the guy was right in front of him, maybe you should stay a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was up to him to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a kind of similar question.
[SPEAKER_01]: I sometimes get annoyed by how others speak to me and feel that they should at least learn how to address others correctly, so that the world in general is a better place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I try to wish them well, but deep down I'm still annoyed, and despite my well wishes, when I engage with the person, my annoyance is what shows itself, and not my good intentions.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because that's the main reason for your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what should I do to better prepare myself for the next time someone says something annoying?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, give up the idea of the world becoming a better place, to begin with.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because why is the world not a better place?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it because people speak bad things?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do people speak bad things?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do people do bad things?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do people kill?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do people lie?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do people steal, cheat, seek gain at the expense of others, enslave others, and all the other misfortune in the world?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do they do that?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's strange.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, because of desire, because of central desire, that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you want to fix the world?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's where you fix it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't fix it by just making everybody comply to your worldview, even if it's a right worldview.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not going to work, because things you're making them comply with, were never the problem, they were the result of the problem of desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's what we said, when
[SPEAKER_05]: Sons fight with fathers, mothers with fathers, husbands and daughters and kings with other kings and everybody.
[SPEAKER_05]: The whole world fights because of central desire, because of desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hate for pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that all comes with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But basically, for as long as you're acting out of your desires, the world will be the way the world is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you want to make a world a better place?
[SPEAKER_05]: Start uprooting the desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: Where do you start at?
[SPEAKER_05]: In others or in yourself?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well,
[SPEAKER_05]: Again, you don't really need to answer that question.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you will be factually making a world a better place if you free yourself from sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: Means there is one being less in this world, massive world, fueled with desire, where there is one person less that has that desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: One desire has been extinguished.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that is factually an improvement.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, one step at a time.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then teach others how to do the same.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then, by then, you would have recognized where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the problem is not the state of the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's just the result of the problem, which is the desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, for as long as you're acting out of the same desires, even righteously, you're still adding the same fuel to the same world, to the same problem of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That view said that the world will be a... get to a stage where it's just a wonderful place, a peaceful place, everyone's happy.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's just your desire, again.
[SPEAKER_05]: And somebody else will come.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't want to.
[SPEAKER_05]: I like the world the way it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's my design.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what do we do now?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, we fight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sooner or later, it will have to lead to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the other one wins, if you end up fighting him.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, whoever wins means...
[SPEAKER_05]: Anyway, you made the world a better place by fighting and violence, which is always what people resort to, eventually, even the most well-wishing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Making the world a better place, well, nothing seems to work.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let's just resort to force.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually quite useful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplation, in a way, because, you know, you can see the things that people do to each other on a very grand scale, like all kinds of corruption, thievery, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can look at it and be disgusted by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when you, if you see, if you realize, oh, like, what's the cause of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: This person is, you know, their actions happen to have these grand repercussions on a huge scale that affect thousands of people because they're in a position of power or something, or it's exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus...
[SPEAKER_00]: That drives me, that makes me act towards something I want, or try to get away, or try to deal with something I dislike.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, even that disgust with the world can kind of make you, oh, like, I should restrain this, because it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that person probably felt the same disgust, which is why he decided to conquer that whole culture and destroy it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, just acting out of the same reasons, completely covering it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Covering up the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're doing the same thing, you're, yeah, as that sutta says, you're partaking in exchange.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're both doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, he started it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: From your point of view, you are the one starting it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_05]: He can't start it for you.
[SPEAKER_05]: No amount of abuse can start abuse, can start, can make you an abuser.
[SPEAKER_05]: Only your actions can then take you in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody can make you get angry.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: And certainly nobody can make you act out of that anger further.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's this verse in the Dhammapada, you know, as long as somebody thinks, oh, he struck me, he abused me, he reviled me.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you do not give up those thoughts, you will not be able to abandon ill will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something along those lines.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the quarrels in the world will never end.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is at the Sutta of the Acrobats, Samyutta Nikaya 47.19.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Blessed One said, once a bamboo acrobat, having erected a bamboo pole, addressed his assistant, come, climb up the bamboo pole and stand on my shoulders.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you say, Master, the assistant answered, and climbing the bamboo pole stood on his shoulders.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the bamboo acrobat said to his assistant, now you watch after me and I'll watch after you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, protecting each other, watching after each other, we'll show off our skill, receive our reward and come down safely from the bamboo pole.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he had said this, the assistant said to him, but that won't do at all, Master.
[SPEAKER_01]: You watch after yourself, and I'll watch after myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, with each of us protecting ourselves, watching after ourselves, we'll show off our skill, receive our reward, and come down safely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, what the assistant said to her master was the right way in that case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monks, for the safeguarding of oneself, satipaṭṭhāna should be practiced.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the safeguarding of others, satipaṭṭhāna should be practiced.
[SPEAKER_01]: When safeguarding yourself, you safeguard others.
[SPEAKER_01]: When safeguarding others, you safeguard yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and how, yeah, it does say, explains it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But no, I won't talk about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I want just an answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: When safeguarding yourself, you safeguard others.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, so why, by safeguarding yourself with mindfulness, you are automatically safeguarding others?
[SPEAKER_05]: How are others not safe?
[SPEAKER_03]: By my acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_05]: By anyone's acting out of your will, greed, aversion and delusion, factually.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there is always... there cannot be no... there cannot be any other route of that non-safety of others, harm towards others.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if everybody would actually just guard themselves, there would be no quarreling, there would be no violence, there would be no abuse, and others would be automatically... the result of that would be safety of others.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if the root of every abuse, every violence, every kind of suffering inflicted upon others is guarded by everybody individually,
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: The world factually becomes a better place.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because there are no more expressions of anger, ill-will, hatred, and so on, and desires, in that sense as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world is responsible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but it's just factually.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not even kind of, oh yeah, we guide ourselves in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Factually, when others are not safe, it's because somebody is acting against that.
[SPEAKER_05]: And those acts can only be rooted in greed, aversion or distraction.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you guard yourself against those, you cannot possibly come near those acts, they would endanger others.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, factually, the world would be a safer place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where does this practically start, for the average?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not killing, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Precepts, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not killing, not stealing, not cheating, not harming, not lying.
[SPEAKER_02]: It actually says that, like by observing these pañca-sīla.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: One gives immeasurable safety to the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Others can trust that you won't kill them, or...
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if they don't trust, factually, to the extent that you're guarding yourself, to that extent, there is no expression of unwholesome towards others.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, factually, the world is a better place to that degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're looking after your bodily behavior, your verbal behavior, a person can still be quite... can still be give rise to that unwholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_05]: Who?
[SPEAKER_05]: That person?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unwholesome intentions, but unwholesome intention is not a danger to others.
[SPEAKER_05]: Acting out of unwholesome intentions is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if your sīla is unbroken, if that's where your effort is, if you restrain your senses, even if you have the most cruel intentions in your mind, you're not acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if now I'm cultivating those cruel intentions, I don't harm anyone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, then you won't have internal peace, but you are still factually not contributing towards the suffering of the world, because you're not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But yes, eventually... Well, it depends.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, we're not talking about necessarily practice for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're talking about making the world a better place.
[SPEAKER_05]: But yeah, if you want to be completely at peace, unable to even have such intentions, then yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But even for that, you still need to restrain yourself first.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, whether you have such intentions or not, the work that needs to be done beforehand remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if your intentions are clean, your mind is restrained, in that sense, then there is absolutely no possibility of acting out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, but in order for your intentions to be clean and mind restrained, you need to have thoroughly not acted out for a long time.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that will.
[SPEAKER_05]: And also, it won't be possible, to be honest.
[SPEAKER_05]: It won't be possible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Theoretically, you could see how you could still have thoughts of ill will and cruelty arising.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you have been thoroughly restrained and withdrawn from unwholesome for a
[SPEAKER_05]: You know, long period of time, mind will have to come down.
[SPEAKER_05]: So those thoughts were besetting you, were coming up, because there was still an opportunity, a hope, that you might give rise to expressing them.
[SPEAKER_05]: But once you haven't been giving rise, those thoughts will come down.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, still the same work, same practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a question in regard to this sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, this attitude of the master acrobat seems like the correct one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, he wouldn't be the master.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, I'll watch you, you watch me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, selfishness does result in harm to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if we can just be unselfish and help others, putting ourselves second,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the society would be a better place, and we would get rid of conceit, which is basically anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this not also a valid path to nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_05]: Hmm, phew!
[SPEAKER_05]: A number of contradictions there.
[SPEAKER_05]: First of all, selfishness is not the reason.
[SPEAKER_05]: Selfishness is the result, also.
[SPEAKER_05]: You are selfish because of the desires, because of craving.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, your selfishness is not the root of all the problems, so you just need to put yourself second.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whether you're first or second, you're selfish, because you're doing it, because you have a desire to do so.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I have a desire to be second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, she has a desire to be second.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, now we're going to quarrel.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have the same desire, but... Yeah, who's the most humble?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: One of them can only be... one of us can be second.
[SPEAKER_05]: We can both be the same.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's not the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Selfishness is the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Put myself second, the world is fixed.
[SPEAKER_05]: See, we all just put ourselves second,
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, then what?
[SPEAKER_05]: Then we are all first again.
[SPEAKER_05]: We are all acting out of our desires to be second.
[SPEAKER_05]: But no.
[SPEAKER_05]: Desire is the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Craving is the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, don't act out of that and then, yeah...
[SPEAKER_05]: But I still... As I said, things will then become clear.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you start practicing like this, you realize, yeah, this is how factually the world is... becomes a better place.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the world will never become a better place on the level of the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because people are not the same, they're not born with the same faculties, not born with the same intent, like states of mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_05]: And some people just will never ever be able to understand these things, or accept them, or restrain themselves.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, factually, majority of the world will always remain in darkness.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's just the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Much like the animal realm.
[SPEAKER_05]: But to that extent, you recognize, even if so,
[SPEAKER_05]: If I remove desire in this creature, and maybe if somebody asks me, I can teach them.
[SPEAKER_05]: If not, well, that's still not my problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: But just to the extent of fixing myself, fixing desire and craving here, the world is brighter to that extent.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that is the most direct, the most verifiable influencing of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says satipaṭṭhāna should be practiced to guard yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're seeing things in the correct order?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, well, yeah, the right view, everything else that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in a way, I thought, there would be seeing yourself, yourself as second, in the right way.
[SPEAKER_05]: Internally, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's not a question of choice, of I choose to put myself second.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just acting out of your desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: But yeah, you can learn how to see yourself second, and then you won't be able to take offense with anyone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you always see yourself as this creature over there.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not your problem, not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's just, I think, that question also sort of, obviously, it kind of shows the different ways in which this, like, protecting oneself is meant, as in, you know, when in a world of
[SPEAKER_00]: Greed and craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Protecting oneself naturally is assumed to mean, like, okay, okay, we're all at a table together and I'm just gonna, like, grab all of the best food for myself first and that's me protecting myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say, oh, you shouldn't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, no, but that's obviously not what is being meant here by protecting oneself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, so we should all share with one another.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, yeah, that's better.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in a sense, what this is meaning is that, like, you should protect yourself by seeing, oh, no, okay, is it...
[SPEAKER_00]: I should just not act out of desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, for my own benefit, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, as a secondary effect, means that I don't really...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not gonna try and grab everything to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might then even still do things like that somebody
[SPEAKER_00]: With a different type of view, you might do like, for example, being generous, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could do that, but you can do that as a kind of a, let me be generous and show how much I'm giving and helping.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, there was that sutta, it said that anāgāmī is doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, he has no wish for heavens or rewards or sensual benefits or something, but he's doing it for a completely different reason that's invisible to those without the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that reason is, oh, it ornates my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the requisite and adornment of the mind, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's basically by engaging in generosity towards others, effortlessly, this mind is embellished beautifully.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, I don't have to bear it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not difficult for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not unpleasant to bear it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's much more easier to bear the mind that's ornate and light and embellished and wholesome.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you realize, instead of
[SPEAKER_05]: It's basically like the... almost recognizing the... which is more efficient effort to elevate your mind, so that you see it clearly and... and exist with it until it breaks apart more peacefully.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you can... you can make this effort, you can make that effort, but generosity... oh, that takes very little, yet the mind is directly, as a result of it, embellished and elevated.
[SPEAKER_05]: And he sees that directly and he does it for that reason and no other.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, no, no desire for reward, no desire for thank you for that matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_05]: It makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_05]: All he wants is his own mind to be elevated on the result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in process without his benefit as well, so... That's the thing, like, when you're... if you're doing it for somebody else, now, if they... if they are ungrateful or if they don't like it or something, I'm affected by that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so you realize, oh, just stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: You carry on doing it, but now learn how not to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because there was exactly preceding was, you know, they do it for the reward, they do it for the heavens, and then to the point of, oh, he just does it for the sake of his own mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it is factually good, generosity also, but it's still worldly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Merit still partakes in the world, in rebirth, in saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it's not the question of, oh, don't do it because you can't do it purely.
[SPEAKER_05]: You won't be able to do it purely because you're not anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, do it whichever way you can, and then what comes as a result of it, you learn how not to be perturbed in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whether it's the expectations of heaven, or being upset because you didn't have enough thank you or gratitude, that's all secondary.
[SPEAKER_05]: You keep doing it, and then you deal with these things on the level of the mind in a sense of learn how not to be perturbed by those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then you will actually grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, and how, when safeguarding others, do you safeguard yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: With yoniso, manasikāra, a mind of metta, harmlessness, and patient endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's all those internal practices.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's what we've been describing, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's just one more question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when I know that my intentions are bad, or that my actions will lead to more suffering, I still don't stop cultivating them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, it seems that I don't really care about myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I practice metta towards myself, will I be able to not choose bad actions next time the intention is there?
[SPEAKER_05]: Putting the cart in front of the horse.
[SPEAKER_05]: Practice of metta will not make you be able to stop choosing badly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not choosing badly,
[SPEAKER_05]: will enable you to stop choosing badly.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you can practice metta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in a way, you're cultivating metta.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's closer to practice of metta than doing metta, so that this is dealt from the same.
[SPEAKER_05]: People want, oh, if I get the jhāna, the pleasure of jhāna that's contemporarily taught, then I will just stop being attracted to sensual pleasures, but I won't have to go through the pains of withdrawal and overcoming them.
[SPEAKER_05]: I just need to get this, so that then this magically falls away.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if I do metta, my bad choices, that I choose, will magically just stop happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: No?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, my decisions will change.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you want to do metta rightly, you start by not cultivating the choices you already, quite clearly, quite well, understand you shouldn't be doing.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you don't care about yourself at the time.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's correct.
[SPEAKER_05]: You obviously lose the context.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, contemplate the danger, peril, obviously, sense restraint, if you haven't developed it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, yeah, the peril will be too much to ignore.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you won't make such choices.
[SPEAKER_05]: You go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this...
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought of bringing up this sutta as well, because it's a how-do-you-know-when's-good-for-you kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people, they keep on doing bad things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they knew that those were bad things, they wouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in some way, they think those things are good.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it brings me pleasure, here and now, later on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or they don't see the extent of how bad they are.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yeah, it's bad, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: But if they were to see the extent of the peril, the extent of the danger,
[SPEAKER_05]: Then they would realize, oh, I cannot engage with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and just to bring up this sutta, which is, how do you see that?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the Rāhula, one of the Rāhula suttas, and the Buddha asks Rāhula, what is a mirror for?
[SPEAKER_01]: And Rāhula answers for reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says, in the same way, Rahula, bodily actions, verbal actions and mental actions are to be done with repeated reflection or consideration.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you want to do a bodily, verbal or mental act, you should reflect on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This act I want to do, would it lead to self-affliction, to the affliction of others or to both?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would it be unskillful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would it be an unskillful action resulting in dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: If on reflection you know that it would lead to self-affliction, to the affliction of others, or to both, it would be an unskillful bodily action resulting in dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then any action of that sort is absolutely unfit for you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the opposite is, if you reflect that these actions will not lead to your self-affliction, to another's affliction, or to both, it would be skillful action resulting in happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, any action of that sort is fit for you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, at the end, he says, Rahula, all those contemplatives in the past, future, present,
[SPEAKER_01]: And all who purified their bodily, verbal and mental actions, did it through this repeated reflection on their actions, in just this way.
[SPEAKER_05]: No other way.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there is no magical thing you can do.
[SPEAKER_05]: They will then purify those things for you in return.
[SPEAKER_03]: Simply doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it exists is a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, practically, whoever has ever done it successfully, they did it through that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha himself did.
[SPEAKER_05]: As the Buddha himself did.
[SPEAKER_05]: Purifying his mind from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_05]: How?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, when there is a sensual lust present, he would establish the context of danger, peril, lack of satisfaction, not beneficial for him, for others, and then the thought would subside, whenever it subsides.
[SPEAKER_05]: That was not his concern.
[SPEAKER_05]: His concern was to protect the context, the framework.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ill-will, thoughts of hatred, context again, of how little benefit that has, how it increases burden for you, how unbeneficial it is, how friendliness is a much better option, letting go is a better option, how all these contexts he would cultivate in face of these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then they would subside eventually.
[SPEAKER_05]: So yoniso manasikāra keeps the context.
[SPEAKER_05]: Endurance, that we often talk about, khanti,
[SPEAKER_05]: Forbearance, patient endurance, whichever you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, so you're enduring the presence of this thought, which is pretty much the benchmark for the context to be developed.
[SPEAKER_05]: Until the thought subsides, not until you got rid of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I got rid of what bothered me.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, you were not bothered by it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why are you trying to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_05]: You're bothered by your own craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: But good luck getting rid of that directly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Attending it or replacing it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Could you be doing that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Be craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then you could do that with... Like I said, the thought would subside on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's very easy to fall into... Like I established the context so that I get rid of this thought because it's bothering me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so there won't be a context.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But so then what would be a better intention?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, to recognize that you've been doing that,
[SPEAKER_05]: And now, upgrade that as well.
[SPEAKER_05]: Establish the context in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_05]: You won't start perfectly.
[SPEAKER_05]: You will be wanting to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But by not acting out, that's already a better context.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's what I was trying to... By guarding of the sense doors, that's another better context.
[SPEAKER_05]: By contemplating the danger of sensuality in face of sensuality, even if you want that sensuality to go away, well, that's a better context than just acting out like before.
[SPEAKER_05]: But now, you really want to approve the hindrances, you have to recognize that, okay, so I am doing this contemplation now, to get rid of this pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that whole thing is painful for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now we establish context in regard to trying to get rid of pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how about then, I start establishing context, that will prevent me, that will remove the attitude of trying to get rid of it, and actually establish the context of worthwhile endurance.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Actually, it is good to endure these things.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not acting out, I'm not proliferating, I'm certainly not welcoming them.
[SPEAKER_05]: So now, I shall patiently endure them, just because I know that whenever I engage with it more, I overstep and activate my own craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what I was gonna basically ask, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, a better intention than, let me establish the context to get rid of this thought, would be, let me establish... Let me establish the context so to not act in whichever way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me establish this context so I can endure this thought in its fullness, in its full extent, as far as it wants to go, without being moved by it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And same for thoughts of ill-will and cruelty.
[SPEAKER_05]: Doubt, as well.